
Implementation Plan: Post-Signup Email Verification (Final)
Goal Description
Implement a frictionless email verification system for Providers. Users can sign up, pay, and access the dashboard immediately. However, their account will be marked "Unverified". They will see a persistent banner and be blocked from taking critical actions (invites, document sharing) until they verify their email via a Magic Link.

Database Changes (Prisma)
[MODIFY] 
schema.prisma
We are adding three specific fields to the 
User
 model:

isEmailVerified   Boolean   @default(false)
verifyEmailToken  String?
verifyEmailExpires DateTime?
Why these fields and expiration?

Security: We need a token to ensure the link they click actually belongs to them. We need an expiration (e.g., 24 hours) so old links can't be stolen and used months later.
Separation: We do not mix this with resetPasswordToken because a user might want to reset their password before verifying their email, or vice versa. Keep them distinct.
Handling Unverified Users After 24 Hours
If a user ignores the email and the 24 hours pass, here is the standard, safest, and most user-friendly way to handle it:

The Solution: You do not delete their account or cancel their subscription (since they are paying customers). Instead, you simply let the token expire and leave them in the "Unverified" state with the persistent warning banner at the top of their dashboard.

When they eventually try to do something critical (like share a document), they will be blocked and reminded to verify.
Since the old link in their email is now expired, if they click it, the /verify-email page will say: "This link has expired. Please request a new one."
They can click the "Resend Link" button on the yellow dashboard banner (or in Settings). This triggers the /resend-verification API, which generates a new 24-hour token, updates the DB, and sends them a fresh email.
This creates an infinite, safe loop where they can always request a new link whenever they are finally ready to verify.
Backend Changes
1. Token Generation on Signup
File: 
auth.controller.ts
 (signupApi)
Action: Right after creating the user and subscription inside the transaction, generate a random 64-character hex token. Set verifyEmailExpires to Date.now() + 24 * 60 * 60 * 1000 (24 hours).
Action: Call an email utility (e.g., sendVerificationEmail(email, token)) in the background.
2. Verification API
Route: POST /api/v1/auth/verify-email/:token
Logic:
Find user where verifyEmailToken == token.
Edge case: If no user found, return 400 "Invalid token."
Edge case: If verifyEmailExpires < now(), return 400 "Token expired. Please request a new verification link."
If valid, update(isEmailVerified: true, verifyEmailToken: null, verifyEmailExpires: null).
Return success.
3. Resend API
Route: POST /api/v1/auth/resend-verification
Logic:
Take loginUserId from the auth middleware.
Find user. Edge case: If user.isEmailVerified == true, return 400 "Already verified".
Generate new token, set expiration to +24 hours, update DB, resend email.
Frontend Changes
1. Universal Warning Banner
Component: EmailVerificationBanner.tsx
Placement: Rendered at the top of 
DashboardLayout.tsx
.
Logic: if (!loginUserDetail?.user?.isEmailVerified) return <Banner />;
UI: A yellow warning bar across the top: "Please verify your email address to unlock all features." with a "Resend Link" button (which calls the Resend API and shows a toast).
2. Settings / Navbar Integration
As seen in your recent edits, the Navbar badge can show "Unverified" based on this new isEmailVerified flag instead of just isApprove.
We can also add a "Resend Verification" button inside the Provider Settings page next to their email.
3. Soft Restrictions (The Blocks)
To prevent unverified users from abusing the platform, we will add UI checks in the following places. If !isEmailVerified, we disable the action button and/or show a Toast/Modal saying: "You must verify your email address before taking this action."

Inviting a Provider (Direct): Disable the "Send Invite" button.
Inviting a Provider to Group: Disable the invite button in the group chat settings.
Sharing Documents with Client/Provider: Disable the "Share" button in the Document Vault.
4. Verification Landing Page
Component: VerifyEmailPage.tsx
Route: /verify-email/:token
Logic: Reads token from URL, calls the Verification API. If success, shows a checkmark and a "Go to Dashboard" button. If fail (e.g. expired), shows an error and a "Resend Email" button.
Verification Plan
Run Migrations: Apply Prisma schema changes.
Signup & Lockout: Create a new provider. Verify they can reach the dashboard but see the yellow banner.
Test Restrictions: Try to invite a provider and share a document. Verify the UI blocks the action with a message.
Test Verification: Click the magic link in the terminal/email, verify the page says "Success", the banner disappears, and restrictions are lifted.